welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
we are going to commence with today's
talk which is brought to us by Michael
Miller Minh just to introduce the stoah
hi my name is Raven and today I am going
to be hosting this talk and very excited
about it I have been very influenced by
Heidegger so this this talk is a
particular interest to me and the
subject today is the current crisis
simultaneously a health crisis an
economic crisis a political crisis and a
crisis of world order presents us with
an opportunity to re-examine some basic
concepts and assumptions about ourselves
the systems in which we live and the
usual ways we interpret the events
happening with us and around us this
talk argues for the relevance of Martin
heidegger's philosophy of another
beginning in understanding and
overcoming the crisis so the way this is
going to work is Michael will do about
20 minutes of of talking about the
subject and then we will open it up to
questions please present your questions
in the chat and indicate if you would
like for me to read the question
otherwise I will call on you and you can
read your question out loud to Michael
and with that Michael handing it over to
you
very much thanks very much so I'll go
through the prepare remarks and then I
look forward to the questions in
discussion so the current crisis
encompassing health economics politics
and world order presents us with an
opportunity to re-examine some basic
concepts and assumptions about ourselves
the systems in which we live and the
usual ways we interpret the events
happening with us and around us nobody
under these circumstances has a monopoly
on sense making I think the stoah you
can see that here individuals groups
info militias to use Jack Murphy's term
and others all have an opportunity to
contribute to understanding interpreting
and influencing what's going on beyond
the constraints and limitations of
traditional channels so one group of
people trying to make sense of what's
going on has tried to bring political
philosophy which is my discipline the
area in which I was trained to bear on
the interpretation of the current
situation for example Benwood finding a
graduate student in political theory in
Montreal has argued that it was our
false illusion of technical mastery over
political affairs that lulled
governments into unpreparedness for the
crisis and he draws here on
Machiavelli's teaching about Fortuna as
a helpful corrective and frame of
reference for that analysis so that's
one example of the use of political
philosophy Machiavelli Karl Schmitt and
Thomas Hobbes I've also been invoked to
help us to reflect on the states of
emergency some governments have declared
and on the reassertion of national
sovereignty we seem to be witnessing as
countries close their borders to travel
and invoke special powers to irrigate
protective personal equipment and other
medical supplies for their doctors
nurses and health care professionals so
all such reflections are to my mind to
be welcomed and within the political
theory tradition we should be prepared
to listen thoughtfully not only to
Machiavelli Schmitt and Hobbes the three
examples I just gave but also to Plato
Aristotle in the Bible as well as jejak
Derrida and doulas and I think you've
been you know Nick glance the abandoned
courtesy Arvin and others and short we
should be willing to listen to anyone
who's thinking about or has thought
about the foundations of human life and
its spiritual political and social
dimensions so that's the first point is
that there's no problem keeping
everything on the table for now
this isn't a talk about having only
Heidegger and everybody else off to the
side and yet what I'd like to bring
before you today is what seems to me to
be in general and neglected alternative
when it comes to crisis sense making at
least among political theorists and
political philosophers in the public
sphere so besides the more familiar
names I mentioned and other approaches
and modalities we can consider during
this time again many of which you can
find at the stoah we should pay special
attention to what German philosopher
Martin Heidegger can teach us about how
to interpret ourselves in our moment so
first as I'm not claiming that nobody
talks about Heidegger I heard him
brought up in a recent event here as
someone who might help us to think about
death and there's definitely something
to that but some of the most important
things he gives us to think about are
often downplayed or ignored
perhaps because they're seen as a
slippery slope to radical right-wing
anti-liberal ism or
or else they're misunderstood for other
reasons the goal ultimately as I see it
is not to talk about Heidegger for
instance with biographical curiosity
about him as a figure of 20th century
intellectual history like his favorite
hat and you know how he got it you
really like for something like that or
even to trace influences but rather with
Heidegger's help to gain genuine access
to ourselves and thereby a better
understanding of the nature of our
crisis broadly construed my claim here
is that we should consider that there's
not only no way out of our crisis but
also no possibility of understanding it
for what it is without a foundation in
heidecker's thaad so now a brief
introductory comments on Heidegger
himself Heidegger who was born in 1889
and died in 1976 also addressed himself
to a crisis so we're not the only people
who have ever lived through what we
think is a crisis in fact you might say
maybe some of the most interesting
thinking happens in the midst of a
crisis or maybe thinking itself always
provokes a crisis if it if it breaks
into the foundations of things but in
this case writing and being in time in
1927 a Heidegger discusses how there was
then a crisis in the sciences including
in mathematics that concerned
foundational concepts and therefore
invited thoughtful
Safa killari grounding and
reconstitution of those Sciences but
that could only happen here argued as a
result of a more basic inquiry into
their structure of being so fundamental
concepts he wrote our determinations in
which the area of knowledge underlying
all the thematic objects of a science
attains an understanding that precedes
and guides all positive investigation so
I'll just explain for instance the
concepts of nature and life are
presupposed by and guide physics and
biology in other words he says all
science is somehow treat a region of
beings or they demarcate or delineate
some area that is given by a set of
fundamental or basic concepts that the
science itself doesn't necessarily
inquire into with its own methods and as
its own subject matter it's a pre
presupposed guiding horizon so
accordingly these basic concepts he
records first receive their genuine
evidence and grounding only in a
correspondingly preliminary research
into the area itself it's a ground the
sciences philosophically in other words
is to clarify the being of their basic
concepts through questions like what is
nature
what is life or for psychology what is
the soul and more fundamentally at the
basis of all of these inquiries what is
being itself the sciences as I said do
not raise these questions themselves you
can't answer them with their own methods
which is why they can't respond to the
crisis and their own foundations it's an
invitation for philosophy to step up and
do the work a crisis in the foundations
of some established an Institute of
domain therefore invites us to
reinterpret those domains in terms of
the constitution of their being using
tools of philosophical analysis that
must also be properly grounded
so the correct methodological access to
the issue of foundations is fundamental
for high agur and in this case we're no
longer simply taking for granted and
assumed area as I said but enquiring
into its basis and structure so for
instance for us and for the question of
sense making or meaning making more
generally that kind of inquiry could
raise the question what is that what is
meaning right what is the being of
meaning what is meaning who are we who
raise this question or as Heidegger asks
in the infant's black notebooks
who are we and whose are we and what is
the character nature or essence of the
act of making in the phrase meaning
making
how does meaning arise and become a
matter of world configuration or world
interpretation and what do we mean by
world at all those are some elementary
increase when we begin to think about
ourselves as meaning-making beings so
there's a complex of questions here you
could say it lies a level deeper then
the questions I take anything about
meaning making for granted including as
I said the issue who it is doing this
activity is it consciousness the soul
the spirit the individual and we could
easily multiply the list of possible
interpretations of the basic unit of
action no bhai degrees suggesting let's
not start with some posited as I say
conscious and soul spirit but let's try
to get a level deeper than that
so what distinguishes Heidegger from the
other approaches is precisely his
recourse through this deeper level of
fundamental ontology where we're always
questioning further into the concealed
presuppositions of our thinking so for
instance we could imagine a conversation
about the contemporary situation that
relies on analysis in terms of something
in Nietzsche
I have nothing against such an approach
and I agree with Peter that if we learn
to be performative lis agnostic and to
maintain such a position experimentally
without holding it ourselves we could
learn important things and gain valuable
insights nevertheless and Heidegger the
question comes to the forefront as to
how the interpretation of being and of
human being is grounded in this case and
in fact Heidegger shows that the
interpretation of being as will to power
for instance to take a fundamental
machen notion is a distorted
interpretation of being in a very
precise sense so let me add though that
he also considered the careful study of
nature to be indispensable and has four
volumes on each of thought and Ponder's
the significance than a range of
writings so it's not just enough to say
well will to power is a distorted
interpretation of being you gotta also
go through the work of studying
Nietzsche but nevertheless he did show
that you can't just operate with
Nietzsche notions because ultimately I
believe he showed this successfully
they're not grounded adequately and the
issue of whether an interpretation is
well grounded remains
we start not with the will to power but
with any such concept like consciousness
or life or race or any definition of the
human being that has not raised the
question of how we stand in relation to
being as such which is always implied in
any definition so not always brought out
explicitly then with methodological
rigor and here another comment for those
of you I suppose who know Peters work or
follow it closely I think you could try
to do this with a helpful chart of
memetic tribes by going through to see
how each of them defines its basic unit
of analysis and its own basic concepts
and deriving these are showing them as
partial interpretations of design and
moreover it could be interesting to try
to use Heidegger's tools as the
foundation for mimetic mediation but i
just mentioned that in passing i do
think that you could do something like
that with with the mimetic drives so the
crisis and the science is that i
mentioned is not the only crisis
Heidegger faced as he writes in his
black notebooks Germany faced an
economic and political play when he
accepted the rectorate at the University
of Freiburg in 1933 but even in the
midst of those crises he thought what
was going on with design and the history
of being she'll say a little more about
in a minute was the essential matter for
Germany and its present and future so in
other words political crisis economic
crisis crisis and the sciences crisis of
the Academy
all of these somehow are fundamentally
rooted in the questions that he raised
about our being in relation to being so
neither the attack on liberal bourgeois
rationality nor any proposed solutions
of a Christian cultural or pagan
völkisch kind touch to the essential
issue at all however much these might
have seemed to some of his
contemporaries to offer distinct
solutions and similarly Heidegger
thought that other apparently opposed
positions like materialism and idealism
or subjectivism and objectivism shared a
common root or rather a common up
rootedness from the experience of being
which was for him the most important
thing so when I read that I wonder
whether so the solutions proposed to our
current crisis however radically opposed
to one another they might appear don't
represent a shared
census largely implicit but there's
nothing to worry about on the level of
da sign and what high degree called the
history beam such that that issue
doesn't even arise or provoke the
slightest anxiety discomfort or interest
the Carl for us to turn to the question
of being could well seem self-absorbed
overly abstract or grotesquely out of
touch with reality in actuality with our
pressing needs here now so you might
very well think body bags are piling up
in people's are our SPS are tanking and
here you are asking us to look into you
know the meaning like that could see him
I would have touched
well Heidegger was well aware that our
everyday attitude toward being had the
tendency to treat it if at all as
something empty and abstract but he
believed that this initial attitude
could if we were not in a hurry to get
away from it the occupy ourselves was
something else
give us a truer understanding of
ourselves than we normally have and here
I have to say I mean I tweeted on the
spot a couple of days ago that the
problem of being it won't like peel an
orange for us it doesn't have practical
immediate practical implementation but
what is to count as a problem for you
how you're to think about it how you're
implicated in it how you stand in
relation to it all of that is patty ER
says compellingly I think very much
bound up with this set questions so
according to Heidegger spot in teaching
in other words in a way nothing matters
more to our systems of meaning and acts
of meaning-making as well as to our
practical political religious and social
affairs then the unthought ways in which
they and we are determined by an
understanding of being that operates
behind our backs
so somehow the unasked question that
stands behind us is closer to us than
our own breath in our own skin if he's
right there's nothing more us than our
relation to being and yet in its unasked
state of distance from us it's over
determining what we're experiencing and
what can become as a stay a problem for
us in the first place um I'll carry on
if you don't mind I'll try to go a
little bit maybe more quickly so I
wanted to introduce two notions of
inauthenticity that we got from
Heidegger the first has to do with the
distinction crucial
him and for us if he's right because
again we're not just reading him as an
interesting philosopher but this is
meant to be an indication we ourselves
are supposed to become more clear and to
ourselves and reading him the first has
to do with the distinction between
beings and being Heidegger opposed
interpreting the human being in terms of
beings which is what he thought many
other interpretations do like the
biological anthropological racial and
psychological ones in a sense liberalism
communism fascism they're all guilty of
interpreting the human being in terms of
beings on this narrowly constrained
horizon
well one form of an authenticity
consists in interpreting ourselves and
the world only in terms of beings as we
usually encounter that non
philosophically so the way we usually
are in the world we are amidst the
beings were among beings we think that's
the way we think that's the way we
operate and one form of inauthenticity
or non self ownership in some sense is
interpreting ourselves in terms of
beings not thought through so as applied
to the crisis that could mean limiting
our view to institutions supply chains
commonly circulating opinions graphical
representations of infections and deaths
you know we've come to become to
fetishize certain chart formations and
so on stock prices and even acts of
government so all of that can very well
capture our attention our interests our
curiosity we can talk about it for a
long time but Heidegger exhorts us
instead or ambition to remember being
even as the technical and organizational
aspects of our problem a pure most
urgent and as death makes itself felt
not to fail to think about the meaning
of our own being towards death so the
first form of inauthenticity
interpreting collapsing everything into
beings into the goings-on without
rooting them the second form of
inauthenticity it has to do with
heidegger's notion of the history of
being and the possibility of another
beginning so just a side note here
basically there are two problems one is
our entanglement in the world that's
where we get caught up with things but
another one is our entanglement in
tradition and handed down opinions about
things including handed down opinions
about being itself so the second form of
authenticity has to do with this history
of
being how did your thought that the
understanding of being itself has
undergone fundamental transformations
since it was first put into question by
ancient Greek philosophers he thought
that in Plato the original experience of
the revelation of being had started to
wane and to conceal itself from the
thinking human so sort of like you had
this moment at the beginning the
philosophical beginning of philosophy
were being reveals itself to the
thinkers and then gradually begins to
pull away or we pull away from being
being pulls away from us it's a motion
in two directions in a sense so he
thought that I was already happening in
Plato and that it continued to do so
through a number of impartial
transformations and one such
transformation in the history of being
according to Heidegger was the momentous
translation of the Greek terms for truth
and its opposite into Latin from which
we get false um and very cos and false
and verify all the English cognates as
ha because as Heidegger shows the new
Latin words reflected a completely
different experience of the essence of
being not different and equally profound
but rather distorted and alienated from
the true experience of falling away and
forgetting a being that became
instituted in language and then other
key transformations occurred in medieval
scholasticism and Descartes and in each
other the point is that even once we've
moved our focus from beings to being
assuming we have done so at all we still
have to make sure we're getting being
itself right and not just operating with
one of its specific distorted uprooted
configurations we can do that throughout
Heidegger called the destruction of
metaphysics which examines all of these
great thinkers from the point of view of
their understanding of being and as we
think about this crisis in our solutions
to it especially on the level of what it
means for the self understanding of
individuals and communities if we follow
Heidegger we should be on guard then
against metaphysical interpretations of
the problem or the solution so for
example our religious revivals already
said supply chains and all of that
that's one temptation just to fall into
the technological organizational side of
the problem of solution but even if you
go to something like a religious
response
Heidegger says we want to beware of an
interpretation of the basic concepts
again like gods soul providence
punishment justice right all of the
potential basic concepts from the
theological domain here would also have
to be grounded in front of mental
ontology likewise you can say an
atheistic response over the atheistic
response rounds basic concepts so let me
jump ahead because I know what I've been
going on and the basic idea is that
Heidegger thinks he has this idea or
project of another beginning of
philosophy so if you do the work of
digging into da sign and you do the work
of digging into the inherited concepts
of ontology there's the possibility or
the prospect of standing before being
itself and inaugurating a new era a new
history of philosophy and he uses this
image that philosophies are like peaks
in a mountain range the great
philosophies are like peaks in a
mountain range they configure the height
the depth and the breadth of the
territory but heidegger's new beginning
wouldn't just be another mountain like
descartes and the rest of them it would
be a new range a a new space time for
thought to configure its own territories
so it's kind of hard to convey not using
an image if you're not already initiated
the Heidegger's way of speaking but the
idea of a philosophy of a new beginning
is supposed to be something like that so
two more quick comments and I'll stop
I've gone over time I know
according to Heidegger which transformed
as a function of the being historical
eras or epochs
so it's only what they've heard that we
can interpret ourselves as subject and
object Nietzsche week interpreter
ourselves as will to power ourselves in
the world and I want to say for the
record this is something like Leo
Strauss is reminder that in classical
political philosophy
most people are determined for the most
part by the type of regime they belong
to so you have not just man a Democratic
man or liberal democratic man Arastoo
Craddock man or you know the Soviet kiss
right Soviet human type human types as
given as a function of the political
regime it's a similar but here Heidegger
is talking about regimes of being so
somehow takes it even a step further and
what I wanted to say in closing here is
that opportunity that the current crisis
presents us with I would say is the
following
if we accept heidegger's invitation to
turn to fundamental ontology as a source
of self understanding
that lies at the basis of our world
order economy institutions of health
systems of everyday life then together
with the deconstruction of metaphysics
we'd have to make the task of another
beginning of philosophy our own and
start to experiment the concept
formation of a design politics a lot of
politics of soil politics is fear but
doesn't politics this prospect is more
radical and less likely than some of the
better-known alternatives and also more
essential the only political philosopher
I know of who's accepted the challenge
openly unconcerned about the supposed
slope to radical right-wing anti
liberalism is Alexander Dugan whose
fourth political theory should therefore
be of particular interest to us in this
our hiding area moment sorry I went on
event that was absolutely excellent so
much richness there I'm so excited that
you're bringing this to the stoah so
that we can begin to think about what
the flaw anew beginning of philosophy is
which I have also found Heidegger to be
extremely instructive in this project
with the question of being as such so I
was wondering though so you're you were
using this word da sign and I think even
for people who have read Heidegger daf
sign and a lot of the terminology that
he uses is mysterious do you mind kind
of describing and unpacking that word
and the particular way that Heidegger
treats it in his work and how it relates
to thinking of being a set so one of the
ways to think about it is that if you
start with the interpretation of the
human being as an individual or the
interpretation of the human being as a
subject or the interpretations of being
a human being as a soul and you want to
say is there some thing on the basis of
which all of those interpretations are
taking place is there something some X
underlying these more potentially more
partial and limited interpretations of
what it means to be a human being and
then you can point out that hypothetical
X you know as da sign so da sign is the
name that we give to the being that
underlies all self interpretations of
the human being as something else that's
one way to see it he says in being in
time that if we are if some
we have begun to wonder about what being
is and the issue is that it's always
implied in what we say and in how we
conduct ourselves so one of his examples
is I say the door is open
well I understand that there's the door
you can't see what I can there's the
door and it's open
I know door I know open and I also know
is Without Really stopping to think
about it right so and and if I say there
is a bird or there was silence on the
mountaintop he gives various different
examples the understanding of being is
always implied so he says what if I
wanted to actually dig into that a
little bit deeper I wanted to get a
fundamental or conceptual grasp on this
being that I always seem to pre
understand well I could look you know if
I wanted to learn about mineralogy I
could look I could go study minerals if
I wanted to do you ocean ography have to
go study the ocean right if I but if I
want to study I want to understand being
is there something that has privileged
access to the question of being and the
argues that it would seem to be we who
raised the question in the first place
we who are constituted with the pre
philosophical understanding of being so
da sign names we ourselves sort of at
its barest level as exposed to and
interested in being prior to the
interpretation of ourselves as something
else
like individual or subject later and
some other writings he hyphenates sign
so that's not - sign and really that I
would say names what we become when
we're transformed by the revelation of
being so it's something so one sense of
a sign is you are you sitting there all
of you listening each of you listening
sitting there is that sign you might
think of yourself as an eye as it you
want to think of yourself as a self you
might have a you know spiritual or your
over tradition or whatever tradition you
interpret yourself through but at the
basis of all of that according to the I
sign I saw in Corita Heidegger would be
what he calls da sign for the formation
of the word is sort of like da has a
spatial component of there and sign is
really the like to be so you are a place
where being happens or you are the
localization of being so that sign is
you got a
don't say like like that it's what you
are underneath yourself interpretations
that can give you access to being itself
if you dig a little it's not helpful so
helpful that word for so long I do want
to open up questions to everybody in the
group so just make sure that I just add
one thing again for the benefit of
people who may so one of the ways
Heidegger um you know defines or expands
on the notion of a sign in being a time
is he says who you are is being in the
world by being in the world as a
composite entity so you are always
already together with world it's not
like in here is a subject oh there is
the world and I must build a bridge from
my inside to the outside and the whole
problem of bridge building therefore it
becomes somatic you see it it's not that
those things are always given together
and composite so we are always already
Co constituted by an understanding of
what world is again understanding means
just initial we may not have turned it
over and over to make it clear but we
always have some understanding of world
and of beings in the world so that's
another way you know that gives a rich
set of things that you could look at
like what is being in for example so
he's Heidegger says a cup okay take a
bowl you know I put I put a pebble in a
bowl the pebble is in the bowl in one
way its mode of being in is like being
inside of a container but the way we're
in the world is not as something inside
a container we're in the world as Co
constituted with the world so he begins
to examine all of these components of
our everyday understanding that we take
for granted and deepens them to their
underlying structure through their what
he calls their existential the
structures of our being okay yeah great
so we've got some questions coming in
and so Peter you have a question here
would you like to ask Michael your
question
so Mikey no I got a double click on the
mimetic mediator drop there mentioned
drop so you have any additional thoughts
on how Heidegger may help with the
mimetic mediation process so I think
that if if he's right that somehow the
basic concepts or units of analysis are
modes of die science itself
interpretation or modes of some more
fundamental underlying you see so if if
we were to treat the high daguerreian
alternative as one of a number of
memetic tribes which it could be you
know at some extent could be the height
against whose yeah on and on about being
you know and they ignore race or
whatever else or you know however you
might set them alongside the others that
is probably something to that but if we
also were to take you know put all of
them in medic tribes horizontally for
example in your imagination right and
with lions going down to this da sign
and sure what is the what existential
structures that Heidegger has identified
like moans of authenticity modes of
inauthenticity modes of temporality
projections of past present and future
you know what is decided on as the
existential moment which I think did you
have a talk somehow having to do with
different modes of time earlier in the
day but if we take that down to
Heidegger's methodological tools I think
we would be able to say to each of
memetic tribes how and basically
remember he comes a lot of the times
he's getting to the foundation by asking
the right kinds of questions so he shows
us for example to his own contemporaries
that both the Communists and the
liberals and the Nazis and Christians
you know each have presupposed some
basic concept that they themselves
cannot account for and somehow there may
be a potential such Socratic type
potential to lead each of the mimetic
tribes into its own aporia you know and
potentially if you lead each of the
mimetic tribes into their own aporia not
necessarily from the point of view of
another of the tribes which you could do
but from a methodological II you know
triangulated position one dimension
below so that was my intuition like I
see
he's doing something similar in a sense
with his own alternatives by showing
that they share a route and not just by
showing it but by giving methodological
access to further analysis and unpacking
and deconstruction and again
deconstruction has the positive
significance of bringing to light what
the foot what the guiding horizons are
so that chart the mimetic
Tribes chart is very helpful I think in
indicating like the key players the key
concepts some key notions right what
even uh even like their bumper sticker
slogans but as I say if we can bring all
of that down to the existential zuv
design and show them as modes of
interpretation it just seemed to me like
there could be something there sparking
a lot of thoughts the other question I
had to pivot to Dugan Hey
another Dugan drop and then just leave
it off so what the yeah you said he was
the only one who's taking up this
process yeah as far as I know I mean I
did write on his topic for my
dissertation at the University of
Toronto it's gonna be coming over as a
book and I did look to see you know I
read a lot about high degree in
political theory high degree in
political philosophy compares a
comparative study of receptions of
Heidegger so I looked at French the
American German and I think that largely
the interpretation of Heidegger's
philosophy has stood in the shadow of
his involvement with the Nazis which I
mean you can understand that to a
certain extent the concern that I he
never denounced as openly or as
vigorously or as publicly as expressly
or as contritely as his critics and even
some of his erstwhile supporters might
have liked you know his involvement with
the Nazis or his support however I'm
qualified in my abend for the Nazis so
somehow I think there was a concern this
is and this is also interesting because
it shows you the geo cultural
geopolitical aspect of philosophy you
see that aspects of heidegger's thinking
were left off the table and I would say
even in some cases systematically
purposefully either repressed they're
distorted because it was thought that
they are how would you put it like
isomorphic or functionally analogous to
you know support for Nazism so if you
think that his being historical
narrative of the trajectory towards
nihilism is leaves you with no moral
political compass to differentiate
between let's say totalitarian and non
totality and regimes or something
because he thinks they're all
totalitarian you know so somehow like
the friend I let me put it to you this
way there's a in again political
philosophy political theory there's a
writer named Allan bloom professor
academic teacher wrote on Plato
translated he translated the Republic
okay translated Plato's Republic wrote
great works on Rousseau and so on
he's got a book called closing of the
American mind and there's a chapter
there called the Nietzschean ization of
the left which discusses how meetcha was
also co-opted by and reinterpreted by
put into the service of leftist
political aims in academia something
similar hide it happened with Heidegger
he was very influential extremely
influential once one guy said in 1980s
that basically all of French philosophy
is completely dominated by Heidegger his
impact is measurable on these thinkers
many of the times when you talk about
postmodern Neel Marxist left or
something like that five steps behind
the figurehead that you see over here
there's Heidegger thinking up on the you
know he's a giant giant force over many
schools of thought where the connection
doesn't even seem clear unless you know
it but it's happened that his influence
has been mostly either the rejection of
Heidegger by liberal centrists or the
reinterpretation of his thought by the
left in the service of unpacking what
they thought were like grand narratives
or so look if they say there's no truth
with a capital T that's it kind of
constructed historically you know
there's no um there's no basis to what
you call metaphysics you thought
metaphysics were stable structures that
you could rely on for your politics like
a politics of natural right just for
example like Leo Strauss has you thought
you can rely on metaphysics or like a
Christian you know politics of soul and
Providence or something but no they
would say these are all contingent they
can be deconstructed and you can shown
that there's that they are all they're
all formations on an abyss so in some
sense the left category ins accepted his
the
construction of metaphysics where he
destabilized the traditional
interpretation of ourselves in the world
but they left out of the picture this
massively essential part of his project
which is the possibility of another
beginning I mean it's more nuanced
to a certain extent and he had some very
good readers on on the Left including
Derrida but roughly the idea of another
beginning was not picked up by anybody I
think largely for political purposes
Dugan is writing outside in a way of the
context of Western European history
after the Second World War
he's less constrained in terms of his
interpretive resources than the French
the Americans and the Germans for sure
so partially the fact that it's a
Russian reception of Heidegger is
already a factor in why they can think
about a new beginning all the more so
when it seems from many geographical and
geopolitical points with you I should
say geopolitical points of view that the
West is indeed going over some sort of
nihilistic cliff or something like that
so and there are things that high-degree
himself said about russia's like
ontological significance so there are
many many factors that line up and Dugan
has also intellectual interests that
somehow primed him before this as is
sort of like anti modern philosopher
king of sorts but it's really--it mark
it's really remarkable because he's
jumped into this project of another
beginning whereas most other readers of
Heidegger don't just not jump into it
they basically won't even acknowledge it
you know or they'll acknowledge it just
to immediately take it down so I think
he's got great relevance for us in
giving us access to Heidegger and to the
latent political philosophical
potentials and Heidegger's thought right
right cool yeah I got a good do good on
the stone I'm stoked it cool thanks man
yeah you're welcome and I gotta say I
mean I just let me just only just add
one thing to that makes Dugan
interesting as a reader of Heidegger so
he's not just saying let's look at you
know some books afterward on the bed
being in time contributions to
philosophy that not not not just let's
read Heidegger but he actually extends
Heidegger's
methods and intuitions so for example
one of Newton's main ideas is that
there's not just the sign but taking his
lead from Heidegger who spoke about
German design for example Dugan
postulates the existential plurality of
da signs in other words people are
different not just culturally not just
cuz they need different fluids and grow
up under you know different climate or
something like that but are
fundamentally all one similar humanity
he tries to trace a difference in the
relationship to being as such among
peoples through an existential analysis
of their language and this is like the
HAI daguerreian foundation of his theory
of a multipolar world so he's taking
Heidegger he himself says he's taking
high degrees methodology and what's
complicit in him and he's very much
experimenting with it actively
cross-pollination 'he's weird
combination superimpositions and it's
pretty interesting
so excellent great thank you so we're
gonna move to key if you would like to
unmute yourself and ask your question
sure hi thank you for going into detail
about this topic that was completely new
to me so I appreciated the way that you
explained it um logically and so here is
the question you kind of brushed over
regimes of being as curious about what
you have to say about that but I also
just wanted to say yay for the
existential plural ooh existential
plurality of design so um that's my
question
okay thanks yeah I you know Dugan has
this passage in the fourth political
theory where he says I don't know why it
is that when I just take a step back for
a minute the idea of a fourth political
theory that he has says neither liberal
nor communist nor fascist therefore
we're going to carve out an alternative
that rejects all of them as inauthentic
versions of human existence constructed
on the horizon for modernity that's
interesting because usually it I don't
know if you've encountered this for me
it was in my face Alfred
the assumption is that if you are not a
liberal and you're not to the left of
liberalism you can only be a fascist
there's no other terminological category
now things have become I probably more
complex to a certain extent maybe even
especially after Trump's victory where
all of these other phenomena had to be
accounted for somehow but Dugan marks of
this this fourth political theory
territory and when he's talking about
this existential multiple see of that
side it's it's of a piece in that theory
and he writes in the book called the
fourth local theory when people hear
about it I'm surprised that they don't
open a bottle of champagne and celebrate
because the possibilities are so
exciting so that's when I hear the yay
for existential plurality I hear
excitement about possible ways of
thinking that may not necessarily be
customary or obvious where you can't
already predict what all the outcomes
will be so I share that I share the
excitement for the possibilities of
thinking as far as the regime's of being
so I wanted to have again strokes on the
record because he's a helpful corrective
to Heidegger in some way but the basic
analogy was that a regime of being would
be like a stage in what Heidegger called
the history of being a phase and era and
epoch where being had been there had
been some essential transformation in
our understanding of being and we
ourselves are interpreted as a flipside
of that understanding of being so for
example this is uh you know he would say
that when modern subjectivity was
constituted in the philosophy of
Descartes and we don't have to go
obviously into the details of how that
happened it's not just the new
understanding of being which it is it's
also a new understanding of human being
so my analogy was just like in Plato as
brought out by strokes but also in
Aristotle the political regimes produce
a political anthropological type like
Liberal Democratic type for the Liberal
Democratic regimes soviet-type through
the Soviet regime fascist fight for the
fascist regime and so on so on collage
eclis there's like the will to power and
the anthropological
version of the will to power there's
mathematical rationality and the as
definition of being but then there's
also the mathematically rational human
being you know so that's the idea of
regimes of being that there's this two
sides of the coin
how we interpret being as such shines a
light on how we interpret the human
being and if there's a history to that
as Heidegger claimed and if that history
is not just arbitrary but actually
represents a falling away from the
original experience of being or an
alienation of being or forgetting a
being then it's very important and then
you can say that you know Nietzsche's
observation that the last man
corresponds to the phase of nihilism is
a version of the Anthropology that
matches our ontological moment or our
how do I put it
ontological regime a regime of being and
so if there is going to if there is
going to be and this is really a future
product project that you know requires
philosophical increase of this type if
there's going to be a philosophy of
another beginning then there's also
going to be the political anthropology
of another beginning and Duggan's worked
on that a little bit I have some
thoughts mostly just following his
experiments and not for now but that's
really what I mean by regimes of regimes
of being could you go into that then
that's okay well into the anthropology
of another beginning or so I mean the
starting this the starting point if we
follow which is follow Heidegger here
would be let's begin with science so
weird again we're no longer talking
about the individual or the community
that's a false dichotomy okay in this
sense cuz that sign you shouldn't
interpret one way or another yet or
about the race or about the nation or
with the state or conscious spiritual
rise on all of the potential things that
you can interpret start with a sign and
we would follow Heidegger in his
existential analysis where he says okay
so we are being being in the world so we
have a specific mode of being in you
have a specific mode of being with being
with each other being with others right
and our being is also as he puts it
always already ahead of itself caring
for things in the world so this defines
our structure it's not just something we
do sometimes not all the times
to be the being that we are is always
already to be ahead of ourselves
projecting having projects and to have
been thrown into existence together with
the world so Dugan for example he has
has a lecture on design politics where
first you presents
you could stay the traditional
Neoplatonic version of politics as a
reflection of the city and speech the
perfect City as imagined by the
philosopher let's say and no that's not
accurate but basically the Platonic city
that's built on the model of excellence
from the top down and then a Haida
garyun city that's built on this
existential foundation from the bottom
up and he sort of does this mapping of
one on to the other you know in terms of
how they see the future whether it's
open or not and all of that so it would
require getting into some methodological
nuance of terminology illogical and so
on but even how we think about space so
about how we think about our about
spaciality you know about the
relationship between language existence
and territory all of that basically
Heidegger we fashions all of that for us
or to use Danna to use maybe a image
that may be familiar to you from
philosophy Plato's Republic where you
have the person who's in the cave he's
chained you can't turn his head he's
only looking at the shadows that are
cast on the wall but he doesn't know
they are shadows he just treats them as
reality it's only once he's seen
something else that he can see them as
shadows well everything looks different
when in the spot where you are you
accomplish a revolution of your soul
because when you're looking at the
shadows that's one mode of existence
when you have performed a revolution of
your soul that's another mode of
existence in other words when you
undergo the turning around that takes
you from what is ordinary and everyday
and customary to the possibility of a
philosophical ascent or a deepening
everything changes and it's similar in
Heidegger our understanding of
everything potentially can change of
power
constitution's search for power of
justice of communities how we identify
the relevant communities of the
relationship between thought and
practice morality and all of this so
even if you think just to say one more
word about this if you say nietzsche has
been relevant to political practice to a
certain extent because he offers a non
liberal antia liberal classical
alternative well if we acknowledge that
Nietzsche has had some effects Heidegger
comes along and he says that Nietzsche
has interpreted the Greek world
completely Roman Lee his understanding
of the political politics is all all
misses the mark and he doesn't just say
it I mean in my view he demonstrates it
as softly as can be done so what this
really opens up is a whole realm of
possibilities for interpreting ourselves
and the world therefore also political
life which is ourselves in the world
right is a certain specific type of
projection of being with others in the
world opens up a whole new set of
possibilities and what's what's
beautiful if I was right about ourselves
what's beautiful about this set of
possibilities is that it's not just
constructed on the sands of something
else that has been constructed on the
sands of something else that lacks
foundation and that can just be another
you know bubble in the foam bubbling up
and you know popping and going back down
to so for something like that it's
supposed to be if Heidegger's right
about ourselves in our interpretation of
being and time this is rootedness and
not in up rootedness you know it's an
understanding of ourselves as we are
truly it would see him and not as we are
seeing through glass darkly
okay well something like that excellent
thank you uh Rachel would you like to
unmute yourself and ask your question
oh yeah so I just had another question
come up after the last discussion but
I'm curious about design
if aura would be a modern human
interpretation of it what are the
differences on where essence would come
so I think that thinking about ourselves
in
of auras in terms of chakras in fact in
terms of the richly elaborated system of
human being available in some systems of
you know of yoga one of the best books I
read a year or two ago on throughly
Neoga had very interesting account of
the chakras and how they configure our
personalities and all of that I returned
to my initial comments where I said
everything should be on the table so I
do think that that interpretation of
political life and of human life should
be on the table in fact I mentioned even
in my dissertation defendants back in
the university days that I think there
should be more political philosophy of
the chakras like thing and they let me
get away with it which I was a little
surprised by but I do think so
however it's not it's not the way that
Heidegger would think about that sign
because it's still it's still looking at
some like mechanical or organic or
biological or psychobiological you know
or even however you put it it's still
for example if you say that it's it
still is in the realm it's the one
interpretation of ourselves taken from
the realm of beings and not from being
as such so he's really not looking for
any like you know this is your subtle
body type interpretation right
and those marbles can get complicated
and they're very interesting like I said
but it's different it's you could ask
about the astral body you can ask about
the being itself of the astral body so
there you already see a distinction
right between the interpretation of
ourselves as or astral body shocker and
so on and the domain that asks about the
being of that so his emphasis is really
on how do we constitute an understanding
of the being as such of anything whether
it's you know the our neuronal activity
our or ik activity our psychic activity
our you know gastronomic activity right
he doesn't want to reduce interpretation
of the human being to any one of those
regions or slices however important is
and he doesn't deny as you have to eat
and walk and you fall in love and all of
that but nevertheless he thinks what's
most fundamental and applied by all of
these is that somehow we think about
them that they are and take their being
for granted they're forced and in some
pre understood notion of being
and that's the domain that he wants to
clarify it so you could you I can
imagine you know some in some distant
future the question imagine you could
put on a pair of glasses and see a
person's aura and see their chakras how
they're spinning how they look what
color they are other inner interacting
with other people's chakras it would be
genuinely very interesting to me
personally to know how does self
interpretation of the regime's of being
and human being look from that point of
view you know I think that that's fair
to ask and I even have some thoughts
about how that might work but but that's
not that's that would be our expansion
of Heidegger's methodology into a new
set of questions and possibilities but
it's not how she interprets that's a
nice kind of follow-up question
okay circle I feel like you're talking
about a my slave genetic occultism sort
of like in the realm of someone like
your other Yaqui but with more of a
scientific explanation is is that right
or am i misinterpreting you I still
think it's too much on a level of what
Heidegger would say beings because it's
not it's not genetic in the terms of
genes and it's not scientific in the
terms of the study of realities or as I
mean there's not a better word for doubt
say than beatings he's saying all of
that take beings as a whole everything
that that is everything about it that
you can say that it is whether it's a
gene or anything else okay he says that
takes the whole domain of beings as a
whole and distinct from beings as a
whole is being as such because all of
these beings they are in being somehow
that's the fact that they are in being
is already distinct from the fact that
they're beings you see what I'm saying
so it takes it takes it's almost like
okay I can remember very clearly where I
was and what I was doing and what I was
thinking and how the world spun for me
so to speak the moment when I myself
conducted des cartes meditation on First
Philosophy okay where you doubt
everything and you get to this
unshakable certainty of your
self it's not like it's actually it
requires like the ice breaks moment or
the penny drops moment it's really not
just it's a total like initiation sort
of or transformation or break
reconfiguration so something like that I
think is helpful in getting this
ontological difference between beings
and being because I can see you're
already tempted to take being into
beings is it the aura is it the genes
you know this is it that it's not any
one thing
and it's not even the totality of things
it's this ontological distinction
between beings and being and all I can
do is indicate it all Heidegger could do
is indicated and in his lecture for
example on Plato's cave a Ligurian on
the essence of truth he says at the
beginning to his students he says you
don't need to be able to speak Greek or
read Greek you don't need to have an
excellent mastery of the tradition of
philosophy that we're looking at here
all that you need at any moment in this
lecture and he says this elsewhere - is
a readiness sort of - on-the-spot
undergo this conversion experience you
know so somehow all that I'm reading
Heidegger and I am I believe this is
true from his earliest - his latest
writings reading Heidegger is being
prepared for a conversion experience but
it's a conversion experience of a
particular kind it's not conversion
experience into one thing or another
it's really conversion into this domain
that's demarcated by the distinction
between beings and being hmm great it
was a great place to end may this be the
origin of a kind of new being for the
people here who have been exposed to
Heidegger right now well Michael thank
you for such a stimulating talk there's
so much so much here to dig into and I
hope that we can continue having this
conversation at stoah about Heidegger
and maybe the possibility space that he
brings to us in terms of thinking and in
the beginning of something
yeah excellent
and the stoah we see this as a gift to
everyone to all of humanity and if you
feel inspired to give a gift to the
stoah you can visit the website under
the gift economy make a contribution
there with that Peter do you have any
other final words yeah go to the website
you can check out upcoming events let's
see if we have do we have we have
collective presencing so it's like a we
spaced practice that's 12 p.m. Easter
time and then we got this badass chick
coming at 10:00 p.m. and she's here
right now Rachel you want to go up mute
and tell us what your events about and
yes I I'm not camera ready right now but
I'm giving a talk on aesthetics and
movements amber gonna cover art
literature music philosophy and how we
getting treated me static movement
during the time of crisis mmm and it
just so happened to be before that the
two hours before that we're gonna have a
session called emancipate the daemon and
I'm gonna be facilitating that one and I
have no idea what that's gonna be about
so we'll find out looking forward to
this all right everyone take care thanks
thanks